Guide to the Albert Edward Elsen Papers SC0569
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Albert Edward Elsen papers
1965-1994
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Elsen, Albert Edward
SC0569
18.75 Linear Feet (15 boxes)
Scope and Content
These papers consist of notes, lectures, articles, and other sources Elsen compiled for the art history courses he taught at Stanford; course readers; drafts of his published works; transcripts of interviews he did with Bruce Beaseley, Kristina Branch, John Davis, Louis Finkelstein, Leon Golub, Sue Gussow, Dimitri Hadzi, James Rosati, Miriam Schapiro, and Kenneth Snelson; subject files on individual artists; and other miscellaneous files.
The course materials were originally kept in 3 ring binders of varying sizes, with some items folded and/or inserted loose into the divisions. The materials have been removed from the binders and foldered according to the division titles; the course title is entered on the folder as the series.
Biography
Albert Elsen, scholar of modern sculpture who specialized in Rodin, was professor of art at Stanford University from 1968 until his death in 1995. He was a pivotal figure in Stanford's acquisition of outdoor sculpture and served as the curator of the Rodin collection.
Mr. Elsen was born in New York in 1927 and earned all his degrees -- bachelor's, master's and doctoral -- from Columbia University, where he wrote his dissertation, "Rodin's 'Gates of Hell,' " under the supervision of Meyer Schapiro. After teaching at Carleton College (1952-1958) and Indiana University, he joined the faculty of Stanford University in 1968.
In a career that spanned more than four decades, Mr. Elsen was known as an expert on late-19th-century and early-20th-century sculpture and as an outstanding teacher and lecturer. He wrote books on Matisse, Seymour Lipton and Paul Jenkins as well as several on Rodin, and two surveys of modern sculpture. His published works include Purposes of Art; Law, Ethics, and the Visual Arts (with John Henry Merryman); Origins of Modern Sculpture: Pioneers and Premises; and Modern European Sculpture 1918-1945.
His former graduate students include many museum professionals, among them Kirk Varnedoe, former chief curator of painting and sculpture at the Museum of Modern Art. Mr. Varnedoe said Mr. Elsen was central in restoring Rodin's reputation, and cited his 1963 Rodin exhibition at the Modern as the moment the sculptor's work "was annexed into the history of modern art."
Mr. Elsen's activities took him far beyond the library and classroom. He contributed frequently to museum exhibitions and catalogues, and served as director of the National Gallery's enormous exhibition "Rodin Rediscovered" in 1981. He was an authority on many facets of the art world, including museum practices, artists' rights, arts legislation, art forgeries and art law.
With John Merryman, a Stanford law professor, he established the first university course on art law in the early 1970's and also wrote "Laws, Ethics and the Visual Arts." And because of Mr. Elsen, Stanford has not only an extensive collection of outdoor sculpture, but also the second largest collection of works by Rodin in the world.
In the late 1960's Mr. Elsen was vocal in the heated art world debate on the authenticity of sculptures made from posthumous casts. As president of the College Art Association from 1974 to 1976, he supervised the drafting of a comprehensive "Statement on Standards for Sculptural Reproduction and Preventive Measures to Combat Unethical Casting in Bronze."
His first marriage, to Patricia Morgan Kline, ended in divorce. He was survived by his second wife, Sharon McClenahan Elsen; a son, Matthew; two daughters, Nancy McVickar and Katherine, and four grandchildren.
Provenance
Administrative transfer from the Cantor Center for Visual Arts, 1999.
Access Restrictions
None.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Administrative transfer from the Cantor Center for Visual Arts, 1999. Gift, 2016.
Art -- Study and teaching.; Artists -- Interviews. -- United States; Rosati, James,; Elsen, Albert Edward; Schapiro, Miriam,; Gussow, Sue.; Hadzi, Dimitri,; Gussow, Sue.; Beasley, Bruce,; Golub, Leon,; Finkelstein, Louis; Branch, Kristina.; Davis, John.; Branch, Kristina.; Stanford University -- General subdivision--Curricula.;; Davis, John.; Stanford University. Department of Art -- General subdivision--Faculty.;; Stanford University--Curricula.; Elsen, Albert Edward; Stanford University. Department of Art--Faculty.; Snelson, Kenneth,
- Papers, Accession ARCH-1999-199
  - Miscellaneous
    - Articles I (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Articles II (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Student Papers I (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Student Papers II (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Photographs (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Class Materials I (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Class Materials II (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Loose Papers (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Articles
    - The Art World as a System - Alloway (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - The Failed Utopia: Russian Art 1917-32 - Bowlt (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Notes on Patronage: The 60's - O'Connor, F. (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Posters of Protest - Kunzle (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - The Burghers of Calais - Ramsden (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - The Liberty of Thought Itself - R.Hughes (Time, 1-Sep-86 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - The Art World - Rosenberg (New Yorker, June 3, 1972) (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - The Masque of Art- Secundus (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - A Different Bohemia - Dowd (New York Times Magazine, 17-Nov-85 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    - Vanity Fair: The NY Art Scene (Newsweek, 4-Jan-65 (Box 8, Folder 56)
    - 2 New York Times Articles (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - My Son, The Lawyer-Gallup (San Francisco Chronicle, 3-Dec-73 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - Causes of Art I (Box 8, Folder 59)
    - Causes of Art II (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - 17th Century Italian Art (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - Picasso - Christmas 1939 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - Onward and upward with the arts (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Megaform in Motown (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - MXD (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Les Synagogues Comtadines (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Sculpture at Stanford (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Death of the City Square (Box 8, Folder 68)
  - Modern Art III
    - Introduction (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Crisis of Impressionism (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Impressionism (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - Cezanne (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Seurat (Box 6, Folder 34)
    - Van Gogh (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - Gauguin (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - Symbolism (Box 6, Folder 37)
    - Lautrec (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - Munch (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - Art Nouveau (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Picasso
    - Cubism (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Course Reader- Part 1 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Course Reader- Part 2 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Course Reader- Part 3 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Course Reader- Part 4 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Course Reader- Part 5 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - The Chains of Artistic Freedom
    - Bowdoin Lecture (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Related Lecture (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Interview with Paul Brach (Box 6, Folder 43)
    - Interview with Leon Golub (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Tyranny of Art (Box 6, Folder 45)
    - Why artists have limited their artistic freedom (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Limited Liberty (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Declarations of Independence & Positive Freedoms (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - Freedom From (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Canons of the Bidden and Self-Forbidden (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Summer of 1993Draft (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Draft- Part 1 (Box 6, Folder 52)
    - Draft- Part 2 (Box 6, Folder 53)
    - Draft- Part 3 (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Draft- Part 4 (Box 6, Folder 55)
    - Introduction (Box 6, Folder 56)
    - Declarations of Independence (Box 6, Folder 57)
    - Freedom From (Box 6, Folder 58)
    - Canons of the Bidden and Self-Forbidden (Box 6, Folder 59)
    - Innocence (Box 6, Folder 60)
    - Teaching (Box 6, Folder 61)
    - Discovery of Freedom (Box 6, Folder 62)
    - Tyranny of Art (Box 6, Folder 63)
    - Expressiveness of the Elements (Box 6, Folder 64)
    - Tyranny of Materials (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - Tyranny of Tools (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - Dictation of Subconscious (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - Why Limits (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - Aging (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Social Duties (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Summary (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Modernism (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Bibliography (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Index (Box 6, Folder 74)
    - Negative Freedoms (Box 6, Folder 75)
    - Discovery (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - Related Seminar (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Chains of Artistic Freedom - Notes
    - Notes from Vasari (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - Commercial Rights (Box 6, Folder 79)
    - Restrictions on Artists' Freedom Before 1800 (Box 6, Folder 80)
    - Occupational/Professional Rights (Box 6, Folder 81)
    - Artists v. Artists (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - Exhibitions (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Restrictions on Artists' Freedom Before 1800 (Box 6, Folder 84)
    - Restrictions on Artists' Freedom Before 1800 (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Rights Available to Western Artists Before 1800 I (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Rights Available to Western Artists Before 1800 II (Box 6, Folder 87)
    - Rights Available to Western Artists Before 1800 III (Box 6, Folder 88)
    - Chains of Artistic Freedom (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Nature and Limits of Modern Artistic Freedom (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Chains of Artistic Freedom (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Expansion on Nature/Limits (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Notes (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - 20th Century Western Art
    - Introduction (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - The Sessions (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Artist's Moral Right (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - The Art Establishment (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Miscellaneous Articles (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Chains of Artistic Freedom-Interviews
    - Beasley, Bruce (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Beasley, Bruce (Revised 8/88) (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Branch, Kristina (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Davis, John (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Finkelstein, Louis (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Golub, Leon (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Gussow, Sue (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Hadzi, Dimitri (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Rosati, James (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Schapiro, Miriam (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Schapiro, Miriam (Revised) (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Snelson, Ken (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Modern Art V- Course Reader
    - Kandinsky's Abstract Style (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Romantic Survival & Revival in the 20th Century (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Mondrian (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Transcendental Abstraction (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - De Chirico & Modernism (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Picasso (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - What About Cubism? (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - The Philosophical Brothel (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Ecole de Paris (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Piet Mondrian (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Russian Suprematism & Constructivism (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Giorgio de Chirico (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Der Sturm (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Synthetic Cubism (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - The Brucke (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Italy and the Modern Spirit (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Les Fauves (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Piet Mondrain (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Juan Gris (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Expressionism (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Art 124- Course Reader
    - Picassso-The Formative Years (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Love and Death in Picasso's Early Work (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Harlequins, Saltimbanques, Clowns and Fools (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - The 'Demoiselles d'Auignon' Revisited (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Philosophical Brothel (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Resisting Cezanne: Picasso's "Three Women" (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Pablo, George, Leo and Bill (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Picasso in the Collection of the Museum of Modern Art (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - What about Cubism? (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - Picasso & Braque (Box 7, Folder 52)
    - Typography of Cubism (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Words (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - Three Musicians (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Classical Period (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - The Three Dancers (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Surrealism (Box 7, Folder 58)
    - Picasso and Surrealism (Box 7, Folder 59)
    - The Anatomy of Eroticism (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - Picasso's 'Cries of Children - Cries of Stones' (Box 7, Folder 61)
    - Three Sculpture Articles (Box 7, Folder 62)
    - The Last 30 years (Box 7, Folder 63)
    - The Musketeer and his Theatrum Mundi (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - The Algerian Women and Picasso at Large (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - The Artist and his Model (Box 7, Folder 66)
  - Environmental Art- Course Reader
    - Part 1 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Part 2 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Part 3 (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Part 4 (Box 7, Folder 70)
  - Course Documents
    - Art I (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - Art 123-30 (Box 7, Folder 72)
    - Art 239 I (Box 7, Folder 73)
    - Art 239 II (Box 7, Folder 74)
    - Art 239 III (Box 7, Folder 75)
    - Art 239 IV (Box 7, Folder 76)
    - Art 239 V (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Miscellaneous Subjects
    - The Artist as a Craftsman (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Black Art (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Chinese Art (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Female Artists (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Modern Sculpture 1945-70 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Public Art (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Painting- Artist as a Craftsman (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Sculptor's Bill of Rights (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Tatlin: Art out into Technology (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Individual Artists
    - Baizerman I (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Baizerman II (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Bloom, Harold (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Brett-Smith, Sarah (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Christo (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Epstein (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Fichandler, Zelda (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Gabo (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Gamboni (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Gambrell (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Golub, Leon (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Hepworth (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Johns, Jasper (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Laurens (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Long, Sharon Rugel (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Maillol (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Reagan, Bernice (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Regan, Donald H. (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Reinhardt (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Schapiro, Miriam (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Smithson, Robert (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Oldenburg, Claes (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Publications
    - Sean Scully-Paintings (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Live/Work- The San Francisco Experience (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Purposes of Art-Problem Book (3 Copies) (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Public Sculpture-Athena Tacha (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Notre Dame's Early Chapels (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Art History -, September, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Metamorphosis in Corneille's Andromede (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - "Art Appreciation" Course Reader (Indiana University) (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - The Analysis of Art- Elsen (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - ART 121A- Course Reader (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Purposes of Art- Draft of Teaching Manual (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Miscellaneous Publications I (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Miscellaneous Publications II (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - "Wonders of Irish Art"-Baldwin (New York Times Magazine, 9-Oct-77 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - "The Search for Simplicity" (SLAC Beam Line, Apr-78 (Box 8, Folder 46)
  - 19th Century Art
    - Introduction (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Mechanix (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Rococo (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - Watteau (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Chardin (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - David (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Goya (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Gros (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - Gericault (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Romantics (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Delacroix (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Impression (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Exam Questions (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Romanesque Art
    - Introduction (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Mechanics (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - Byzantine II (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - Ottonian (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - Rhenish (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - English 10th-11th Century (Box 4, Folder 132)
    - Monasteries (Box 4, Folder 133)
    - Medieval Cities (Box 4, Folder 134)
    - Romanesque Architecture (Box 4, Folder 135)
    - Romanesque Sculpture (Box 4, Folder 136)
    - Murals (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - MSS (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Meaning of Gothic Architecture (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Gothic Architecture (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Space (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Gothic Sculpture (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Gothic Painting (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Human Art
    - 16th-17th Centuries (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Good Life- Baroque Art (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Rembrandt (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Ruler (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Architecture of Authority (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Public Spaces (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Palladio/Wright (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - 19th Century Painting (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Nature (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Objects (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Portraits (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Figure in Sculpture (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Picasso (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Abstract/Fantasy Art (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Art History
    - Introduction (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - The Artist (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Magic- Tribal Art (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Gods (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Signs (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Sacred Architecture (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Manuscripts (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - The 15th Century (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Michaelangelo (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Counter-References (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Kings (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Katsura (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Public Spaces (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - The 19th Century (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Nature (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Object (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Portraits (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Figure in Sculpture (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Picasso (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Imaginative Art (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Interwar Painting
    - Modern and Abstract Art (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Constructivist (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Counter-Modern Movement (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Beckmann (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Dada (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Surrealism (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Miro (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Masson (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Dubuffet (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Picasso II (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Medieval Art II
    - Introduction (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Mechanix II (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Hiberno-Saxon (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Merovingian (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Carolingian (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Carolingian Architecture (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - Syllabus (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Mechanix (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - General Observations (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - Held Review (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - Med. Trans-MSS (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - Sluter (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - Philosophy (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - History & Cities (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Flemish Culture (Box 5, Folder 67)
    - Guilds & Techniques (Box 5, Folder 68)
    - Symbolism (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Campin (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - Van Eyck (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Roger V.D. Weyden (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - Christus, Bouts (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - Van Der Goes (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Memling, David (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Bosch (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - 15th Century France (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - Graphic Art (Box 5, Folder 78)
    - German Painting and Sculpture (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Grunewald (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - Modern European Painting
    - Introduction (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Fauves (Box 5, Folder 82)
    - Matisse (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - German Sculpture (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Kandinsky (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Picasso & Cubism (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Delaunay (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - Orphism (Box 5, Folder 88)
    - Futurism (Box 5, Folder 89)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - Renaissance Art
    - Mechanix (Box 5, Folder 91)
    - General (Box 5, Folder 92)
    - Giotto (Box 5, Folder 93)
    - 14th Century Space (Box 5, Folder 94)
    - Masaccio (Box 5, Folder 95)
    - Abstract Devices (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - Brunelleschi (Box 5, Folder 97)
    - Alberti (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Ghiberti (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Donatello (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - Religion and Genre (Box 5, Folder 101)
    - Portraits (Box 5, Folder 102)
    - Uccello (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - Veneziano (Box 5, Folder 104)
    - Piero (Box 5, Folder 105)
    - Castagno (Box 5, Folder 106)
    - Pollaniolo (Box 5, Folder 107)
    - Ghirladaio (Box 5, Folder 108)
    - Mentegna (Box 5, Folder 109)
    - Botticelli (Box 5, Folder 110)
    - Leonardo (Box 5, Folder 111)
    - Raphael (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - European Painting, 1880-1900
    - Mechanix IV (Box 5, Folder 113)
    - Against Impressionism (Box 5, Folder 114)
    - Impressionism (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - Monet (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Cezanne (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Seurat (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Van Gogh (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - Gauguin (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - Gauguin Continued (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - Nabis/Symbolism (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - Redon (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - Lautrec (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Ensor (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Munch (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Seitz (Box 5, Folder 127)
  - Art Appreciation
    - Introduction (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Definitions & Prejudices (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Style, Form & Elements (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Aesthetics (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Value Judgments (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Meaning in Art (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Reality in Art (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Prov. For Play (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Child Art (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Magic (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Landscape Painting (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Still Life (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Necessity for Art (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - City & Capitol (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Portal and Portrait (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Deific Presence (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Art for Good (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Release, Reunion, and Revelation of the Hidden Good (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Synthesis of Celestial and Terrestrial Values (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Propaganda (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Apocalypse, Cataclysm, & Hell (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Church and Temple (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Images of God (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Modernism
    - Introduction (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Folder 2 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Abstract Expressionism
    - Introduction (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Abstract Expressionism - General (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Gorky (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - de Kooning (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Newman (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Still (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Modern Art V
    - Introduction (Box 3, Folder 50)
    - Schapiro: Abstract Art (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Recap: 1880-1900 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Fauves (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - Matisse (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Picasso (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Cubism (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Leger (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Orphism (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Mondrian & D.S. (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Futurism (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Di Chirico (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Chagall (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Expressionism (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Kandinsky (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Malevich (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - El Lissitzky (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Exter (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Rodin
    - Introduction (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Analysis Sheet (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Charles Blanc (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Modern Sculpture
    - Primitivism (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Barlach (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Nadelman (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Brancusi (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Modigliani (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Epstein (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Gaudier (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Archipenko (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Duchamp-Villon (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Picasso (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Lipchitz (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Boccioni (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Ideas- Form in Interwar Art
    - Ideas-Show (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Period (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Questions (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Exemplary Figures (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Monuments (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - History & Sculpture (Box 4, Folder 18)